Two hundred years of modern science.
مائتي سنة من العلم الحديث
We have to admit
علينا أن نعترف
that our performance is not great.
أنّ أدائنا ليس جيداً
The machines we build continue to suffer from mechanical failures.
الآلات التي نصنعها لا تزال تعاني من أعطال ميكانيكية.
The houses we build do not survive severe earthquakes.
البيوت التي نبنيها لا تتحمّل الزّلازل العنيفة.
But we shouldn't be so critical of our scientists for a simple reason:
لكن لا ينبغي أن ننتقد علمائنا لسبب بسيط
they didn't have much time.
لم يكن لديهم الكثير من الوقت.
Two hundred years is not a lot of time,
مائتي سنة لا تكفي
while nature had three billion years
في حين أن الطبيعة امتلكت 3 مليارات سنة
to perfect some of the most amazing materials,
لإتقان أكثر المواد إذهالاً
that we wish we had in our possession.
والتي نودّ لو كانت بحوزتنا
Remember, these materials carry a quality assurance
تذكّر، هذه المواد تحمل ضمان للجودة
of three billion years.
عمره ثلاثة مليارات سنة.
Take, for example, sequoia trees.
خذ على سبيل المثال، أشجار السيكويا
They carry hundreds of tons for hundreds of years
تحمل مئات الأطنان لمئات السنين
in cold weather, in warm climates,
مُتحمّلةً الطقس البارد والمناخات الدافئة
UV light.
والأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
Yet, if you look at the structure by high-resolution electron microscopy,
و اذا نظرت إلى بُنيتها بواسطة مجهر إلكتروني عالي الدقة،
and you ask yourself, what is it made of,
وسألت نفسك، مصنوعةٌ من ماذا؟
surprisingly, it's made of sugar.
المفاجأة، أنّها مصنوعة من السكر
Well, not exactly as we drink in our tea.
حسناً، ليس تماماً كالذي نشربه في الشاي.
It's actually a nanofiber called nanocrystalline cellulose.
إنه عبارة عن ألياف نانوية تسمّى نانوكريستالين سيلولوز
And this nanocrystalline cellulose is so strong, on a weight basis,
وهذا النانوكريستالين سيلولوز قويّ جداً من حيث تحمّله للأوزان
it's about 10 times stronger than steel.
فهو أقوى من الفولاذ بعشر مرّات
Yet it's made of sugar.
نعم, تلك الألياف مصنوعة من السكر
So scientists all over the world believe that nanocellulose
يؤمن العلماء في جميع أنحاء العالم أن النانوسيلولوز
is going to be one of the most important materials for the entire industry.
سيصبح واحداً من أهم المواد في جميع مجالات الصناعة
But here's the problem:
ولكن هنا تكمن المشكلة
say you want to buy a half a ton of nanocellulose
لنقل أنك تريد شراء نصف طن من النانوسيلولوز
to build a boat or an airplane.
لبناء قارب أو طائرة.
Well, you can Google, you can eBay, you can even Alibaba.
حسناً، ستبحث في مواقع غوغل و إيباي و حتى موقع علي بابا
You won't find it.
لن تجده.
Of course, you're going to find thousands of scientific papers --
بالطّبع، سوف تعثر على الآلاف من الأبحاث العلمية
great papers, where scientists are going to say this is a great material,
أبحاث عظيمة، يوضّح فيها العلماء عظَمة هذه المادة
there are lots of things we can do with it.
يمكننا فعل الكثير بهذه المادة
But no commercial source.
لكن لا يوجد مصدر تجاري
So we at the Hebrew University, together with our partners in Sweden,
لذلك نحن في الجامعة العبرية، سوياً مع شركائنا في السويد،
decided to focus on the development of an industrial-scale process
قررنا أن نركّز على تطوير معيار صناعي من أجل
to produce this nanocellulose.
إنتاج هذا النانوسيلولوز.
And, of course, we didn't want to cut trees.
وبالطيع، لم نُرِد قطع الأشجار.
So we were looking for another source
فبحثنا عن مصدر آخر
of raw material,
للمواد الخام
and we found one -- in fact, the sludge of the paper industry.
في الواقع, وجدنا واحداً وهو مخلّفات مصانع الورق
The reason: there is a lot of it.
السبب أنّ هناك الكثير منها
Europe alone produces 11 million tons
أوروبا وحدها تنتج 11 مليون طن
of that material annually.
من هذه المادة سنوياً
It's the equivalent of a mountain three kilometers high,
ما يعادل جبلاُ بارتفاع ثلاثة كيلومترات
sitting on a soccer field.
قاعدته ملعبٌ لكرة القدم.
And we produce this mountain every year.
هذا الجبل يتم إنتاجه كلّ عام.
So for everybody, it's an environmental problem,
برأي الجميع, إنها مشكلة بيئيّة
and for us, it's a gold mine.
وبالنسبة لنا، إنها منجم ذهب
So now, we are actually producing, on an industrial scale in Israel,
الآن، نحن نقوم بإنتاج النانوسيلولوز بمعايير صناعية في إسرائيل
nanocellulose, and very soon, in Sweden.
وقريباً جداً، في السويد.
We can do a lot of things with the material.
يمكننا أن نفعل الكثير من الأشياء مع المواد
For example,
على سبيل المثال
we have shown that by adding only a small percent of nanocellulose
لقد أظهرنا أنّ إضافة نسبة صغيرة من النانوسيلولوز
into cotton fibers, the same as my shirt is made of,
إلى ألياف القطن نفسها التي صُنع منها قميصي
it increases its strength dramatically.
يزيد قوتها بشكل كبير
So this can be used for making amazing things,
فيمكن استخدامها لصنع أشياء مدهشة،
like super-fabrics for industrial and medical applications.
مثل الأقمشة الفائقة للتطبيقات الصناعية والطبية
But this is not the only thing.
ولكن هذا ليس الشيء الوحيد.
For example, self-standing, self-supporting structures,
مثلاً, المباني التي تقف وتدعم نفسها ذاتيّاً
like the shelters that you can see now,
كالملاجئ التي تراها الآن،
actually are now showcasing in the Venice Biennale for Architecture.
في الواقع هي معروضة الآن في معرض بينالي البندقية للعمارة.
Nature actually didn't stop its wonders
عجائب الطبيعة في الواقع لم تتوقف عند
in the plant kingdom.
المملكة النباتية
Think about insects.
فكروا في الحشرات.
Cat fleas, for example,
براغيث القطط ، على سبيل المثال
have the ability to jump about a hundred times their height.
لديهم القدرة على القفز مسافة تساوي مئة ضعف طولهم
That's amazing.
هذا رائع
It's the equivalent of a person
و هو ما يعادل شخصاً
standing in the middle of Liberty Island in New York,
واقفاً في وسط جزيرة الحرية في نيويورك
and in a single jump,
و بقفزة واحدة
going to the top of the Statue of Liberty.
يصل إلى قمته
I'm sure everybody would like to do that.
أنا متأكد أن الجميع يرغب في فعل ذلك.
So the question is:
لذا فإن السؤال هو:
How do cat fleas do it?
كيف تفعل براغيث القطط ذلك؟
It turns out, they make this wonderful material,
إتّضح، أنهم يُنتجون هذه المادة المذهلة،
which is called resilin.
التي تُدعى (ريزيلين)
In simple words, resilin, which is a protein,
ببساطة, الريزيلين هو بروتين
is the most elastic rubber on Earth.
و هو المطاط الأكثر مرونة على الأرض.
You can stretch it,
يمكنك مطّه
you can squish it,
يمكنك سحقه
and it doesn't lose almost any energy to the environment.
ولا يفقد أي طاقة تقريباً
When you release it -- snap!
وعند تحريره, فجأة!
It brings back all the energy.
فإنه يُعيد كل الطاقة.
So I'm sure everybody would like to have that material.
لذا أنا متأكد أن الجميع يرغب في الحصول على تلك المادة.
But here's the problem:
لكن هنا تكمن المشكلة
to catch cat fleas is difficult.
فمن الصعب القبض على براغيث القطط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Why? Because they are jumpy.
لماذا؟ لأنهم يقفزون دائماً.
But now, it's actually enough to catch one.
ولكن الآن، يكفي القبض على واحد.
Now we can extract its DNA
الآن يمكننا إستخراج حمضهم النووي
and read how cat fleas make the resilin,
ومعرفة كيف تصنع براغيث القطط الريزيلين
and clone it into a less-jumpy organism like a plant.
وإستنساخه عن طريق كائن حي أقل قفزاً مثل النبات
So that's exactly what we did.
هذا هو بالضبط ما فعلناه
Now we have the ability to produce lots of resilin.
الآن لدينا القدرة على إنتاج الكثير من الريزيلين.
Well, my team decided to do something really cool at the university.
حسناً، فريقي قرر أن يفعل شيئاً مميزاً في الجامعة.
They decided to combine
قرّروا الجمع بين
the strongest material produced by the plant kingdom
أقوى المواد التي أنتجتها المملكة النباتية
with the most elastic material produced by the insect kingdom --
مع أكثر المواد المرنة التي أنتجتها مملكة الحشرات
nanocellulose with resilin.
النانوسيليولز مع الريزيلين
And the result is amazing.
والنتيجة مذهلة
This material, in fact, is tough, elastic and transparent.
في الواقع هذه المادة, قاسية ومرنة وشفافة.
So there are lots of things that can be done with this material.
لذلك هناك الكثير من الأشياء التي يمكن أن تُصُنع بهذه المادة.
For example, next-generation sport shoes,
مثلاً، الجيل القادم من الأحذية الرياضية
so we can jump higher, run faster.
سنستطيع أن نقفز مسافة أعلى ونجري بشكل أسرع
And even touch screens for computers and smartphones,
وحتى شاشات اللمس لأجهزة الكمبيوتر والهواتف الذكية،
that won't break.
و التي لن تنكسر
Well, the problem is, we continue to implant
حسناً، المشكلة هي أننا نستمر في زرع
synthetic implants in our body,
أشياء اصطناعية في جسمنا
which we glue and screw into our body.
ونضع الغراء والمسامير فيه
And I'm going to say that this is not a good idea.
وأريد أن أقول أن هذه ليست فكرة جيدة.
Why? Because they fail.
لماذا؟ لأنها فاشلة
This synthetic material fails,
هذه المواد الاصطناعية فاشلة
just like this plastic fork,
تماماً مثل هذه الشوكة البلاستيكية
that is not strong enough for its performance.
ليست قوية بما يكفي لأداء عملها.
But sometimes they are too strong,
وأحياناً كون قوية جداً،
and therefore their mechanical properties do not really fit
وبالتالي خصائصها الميكانيكة لا تتلائم
their surrounding tissues.
مع الأنسجة المحيطة بها
But in fact, the reason is much more fundamental.
في الواقع، السبب يتعلق بأصل الجسم
The reason is that in nature,
ففي الطبيعة
there is no one there
لا يوجد أحد
that actually takes my head and screws it onto my neck,
يأخذ رأسي ويثبّته في رقبتي بالمسامير
or takes my skin and glues it onto my body.
أو يأخذ جلدي ويلصقه على جسدي.
In nature, everything is self-assembled.
في الطبيعة، كل شيء مُجمّع ذاتياً.
So every living cell,
إذاً كلّ خليّة حيّة،
whether coming from a plant, insect or human being,
سواء كانت قادمةً من نبات أو حشرة أو إنسان
has a DNA that encodes for nanobio building blocks.
لديها حمض نووي يحوي الشيفرة الوراثية لصنع أجزائها المختلفة
Many times they are proteins.
وهي بروتينات غالباً
Other times, they are enzymes that make other materials,
وفي أحيان أخرى، هي أنزيمات تصنع مواد أخرى
like polysaccharides, fatty acids.
مثل السكريات والأحماض الدهنية
And the common feature about all these materials
والميزة المشتركة بين جميع هذه المواد
is that they need no one.
هي أنّهم لا يحتاجون أحداً
They recognize each other and self-assemble
فهم يجمّعون بعضهم البعض بشكل ذاتي
into structures -- scaffolds on which cells are proliferating
في هياكل، على شكل سقالات تبدأ الخلايا بالتكاثر عليها
to give tissues.
لإعطاء الأنسجة
They develop into organs, and together bring life.
حتى تتطور إلى أعضاء، وجنباً إلى جنب يشكلون الحياة.
So we at the Hebrew University, about 10 years ago, decided to focus
لذلك نحن في الجامعة العبرية، قررنا منذ 10 أعوام أن نركّز
on probably the most important biomaterial for humans,
على أهم مادة بيولوجية عند الإنسان،
which is collagen.
وهي الكولاجين.
Why collagen?
لماذا الكولاجين؟
Because collagen accounts for about 25 percent of our dry weight.
لأن الكولاجين يشكل نحو 25 في المئة من وزننا الجاف.
We have nothing more than collagen, other than water, in our body.
اذا استثنينا الماء, فليس لدينا شيء أكثر من الكولاجين في أجسامنا
So I always like to say,
لذلك أحبّ أن أقول دائماً
anyone who is in the replacement parts of human beings
أنّ أيّ شخص يهتم باستبدال الأعضاء البشرية
would like to have collagen.
سيرغب بالحصول على الكولاجين.
Admittedly, before we started our project,
لا ننكر أنه وقبل بداية مشروعنا
there were already more than 1,000 medical implants
كان هناك بالفعل أكثر من 1000 عملية زرع طبية
made of collagen.
أساسها كان الكولاجين
You know, simple things like dermal fillers to reduce wrinkles,
أشياء بسيطة مثل الحشو الجلدي للتخفيف من التجاعيد
augment lips,
نفخ الشفاه
and other, more sophisticated medical implants, like heart valves.
وعمليات أكثر تطوراً مثل زرع صمامات القلب
So where is the problem?
إذاً أين هي المشكلة؟
Well, the problem is the source.
حسناً، المشكلة هي المصدر.
The source of all that collagen
إنّ كلّ ذلك الكولاجين
is actually coming from dead bodies:
بالواقع يأتي من الجثث
dead pigs, dead cows
الخنازير والأبقار الميتة
and even human cadavers.
وحتى الجثث البشرية.
So safety is a big issue.
بالتالي فإنّ السلامة هي من أهم القضايا
But it's not the only one.
لكنها ليست الوحيدة.
Also, the quality.
أيضاً، الجودة.
Now here, I have a personal interest.
الآن هنا، لدي مصلحة شخصية.
This is my father, Zvi, in our winery in Israel.
هذا هو والدي (زفي) في مصنعنا للخمر في إسرائيل
A heart valve, very similar to the one that I showed you before,
صمام للقلب, مشابه للذي أريتكم إياه من قبل
seven years ago, was implanted in his body.
تم زرعه في جسمه منذ سبع سنوات
Now, the scientific literature says that these heart valves start to fail
الآن، الأبحاث العلمية تقول أن هذه الصمامات القلبية تبدأ بالتخرّب
10 years after the operation.
بعد عشرة أعوام من العملية
No wonder:
لا عجب
they are made from old, used tissues,
إنها مصنوعة من أنسجة قديمة ومستخدمة
just like this wall made of bricks that is falling apart.
تماماً مثل هذا الجدار المصنوع من الطوب والذي يوشك على السقوط
Yeah, of course, I can take those bricks and build a new wall.
نعم، بالطبع، يمكنني أخذ تلك الطوب وبناء جدار جديد
But it's not going to be the same.
ولكنه لن يكون مثله.
So the US Food and Drug Administration
الهيئة الأمريكية للغذاء و الدواء
made a notice already in 2007,
أصدرت بياناً في عام 2007،
asking the companies to start to look for better alternatives.
طالبةً من الشركات أن تبحث عن بدائل أفضل.
So that's exactly what we did.
هذا بالضبط ما فعلناه.
We decided to clone all the five human genes responsible
قررنا استنساخ الجينات البشرية الخمس المسؤولة
for making type I collagen in humans
عن تكوين النمط الأول من الكولاجين
into a transgenic tobacco plant.
في نبات التبغ المعدل وراثياً.
So now, the plant has the ability to make human collagen brand new,
الآن، النبات لديه القدرة على صنع كولاجين بشري جديد كلّيّاً
untouched.
و طازج.
This is amazing.
هذا رائع
Actually, it's happening now.
في الواقع نحن نقوم بذلك حاليّاً
Today in Israel, we grow it in 25,000 square meters of greenhouses
اليوم في إسرائيل نزرعه في مساحة 25,000 متر مربع من البيوت البلاستيكية
all over the country.
في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
The farmers receive small plantlets of tobacco.
المزارعين يحصلون على شتلات صغيرة من التبغ.
It looks exactly like regular tobacco,
تبدو تماماً مثل التبغ العادي،
except that they have five human genes.
باستثناء أن هذه الشتلات تملك خمسة جينات بشرية.
They're responsible for making type I collagen.
مسؤولة عن صنع النمط الأول من الكولاجين.
We grow them for about 50 to 70 days,
نزرع الشتلات لمدة 50-70 يوماً
we harvest the leaves,
نحصد الأوراق
and then the leaves are transported by cooling trucks to the factory.
وبعد ذلك يتم نقل الأوراق بشاحنات مُبرّدة إلى المصنع.
There, the process of extracting the collagen starts.
هناك، تبدأ عملية استخراج الكولاجين.
Now, if you ever made a pesto -- essentially, the same thing.
الآن، إذا صنعتَ من قبل صلصة البيستو فالأمر مشابه هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You crush the leaves, you get the juice that contains the collagen.
تطحن الأوراق، وتحصل على العصير الذي يحوي الكولاجين.
We concentrate the protein,
نقوم بتركيز البروتين،
transfer the protein to clean rooms for the final purification,
ننقل البروتين لغرفة نظيفة للتنقية النهائية،
and the end result is a collagen identical to what we have in our body --
والنتيجة هي كولاجين مطابق للكولاجين في أجسامنا
untouched, brand new
طازج و جديد كُلّياً
and from which we make different medical implants:
ومنه نقوم بإنتاج الأنسجة المزروعة المختلفة
bone void fillers, for example,
المواد المالئة للعظم مثلاً
for severe bone fractures, spinal fusion.
لحالات كسور العظام الشديدة ودمج الفقرات من العمود الفقري
And more recently, even,
وفي الآونة الأخيرة
we've been able to launch into the market here in Europe
كنا قادرين على إطلاق مادة جديدة في السوق الأوروبية
a flowable gel that is used for diabetic foot ulcers,
وهي مادة هلامية يتم إستخدامها لقرحة القدم السكرية
that is now approved for use in the clinic.
والآن تمت الموافقة على استخدامها في العيادات
This is not science fiction.
هذا ليس خيالاً علمياً.
This is happening now.
هذا يحدث الآن
We are using plants to make medical implants
نحن نستخدم النباتات لصنع الطعوم الطبية
for replacement parts for human beings.
واستخدامها لاستبدال الأنسجة البشرية المتضررة
In fact, more recently, we've been able to make collagen fibers
في الآونة الأخيرة أصبحنا قادرين على صنع ألياف الكولاجين
which are six times stronger than the Achilles tendon.
وهي أقوى بست مرّات من وتر آشيل
That's amazing.
هذا رائع.
Together with our partners from Ireland,
جنباً إلى جنب مع شركائنا من أيرلندا
we thought about the next thing:
فكرنا بالخطوة القادمة
adding resilin to those fibers.
وهي إضافة الريزيلين لتلك الألياف.
By doing that,
بفعل ذلك
we've been able to make a superfiber
أصبحنا قادرين على صنع ألياف خارقة
which is about 380 percent tougher,
ألياف أكثر قوة بنسبة 380 في المئة،
and 300 percent more elastic.
وأكثر مرونة بنسبة 300 في المئة
So oddly enough, in the future,
ما يدعو للاستغراب أنّه في المستقبل
when a patient is transplanted with artificial tendons or ligaments
عندما يتم زرع أوتار أو أربطة صناعية عند مريض
made from these fibers,
مصنوعة من هذه الألياف
we'll have better performance after the surgery
سيكون الأداء بعد الجراحة
than we had before the injury.
أفضل من الأداء قبل حدوث الإصابة
So what's for the future?
إذاً ماذا عن المستقبل؟
In the future, we believe we'll be able to make
في المستقبل، نحن نؤمن بقدرتنا على إنتاج
many nanobio building blocks that nature provided for us --
العديد من الجزيئات البيولوجية التي تقدمها لنا الطبيعة
collagen, nanocellulose, resilin and many more.
الكولاجين، النانوسيلولوز، الريزيلين وغيرها الكثير.
And that will enable us to make better machines perform better,
والتي سوف تمكننا من صناعة آلات أفضل بأداء أفضل،
even the heart.
حتى القلب.
Now, this heart is not going to be the same
هذا القلب لن يكون نفسه
as we can get from a donor.
كالذي نحصل عليه من أحد المتبرعين
It will be better.
بل سيكون أفضل.
It actually will perform better
في الواقع سوف يعطي أداءً أفضل
and will last longer.
وسيعيش لفترة أطول.
My friend Zion Suliman once told me
صديقي (صهيون سليمان) قال لي ذات مرة
a smart sentence.
جملةً ذكيةً
He said, "If you want a new idea,
قال: "إذا كنت تريد فكرة جديدة،
you should open an old book."
عليك بفتح كتاب قديم ".
And I'm going to say that the book was written.
دعوني أقول لكم أن الكتاب مكتوب.
It was written over three billion years
وتمت كتابته خلال أكثر من ثلاثة مليارات سنة
of evolution.
من التطور.
And the text is the DNA of life.
والنص هو الحمض النووي
All we have to do
كل ما علينا القيام به
is read this text,
هو قراءة هذا النص،
embrace nature's gift to us
معانقة هدية الطبيعة لنا
and start our progress from here.
وسيبدأ تقدمنا من هنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)